[Applause]
[Music]
I'm a psychologist and a neuroscientist
by training when I first began my career
I began with a question why is it that
some people are more vulnerable to
life's slings and arrows and others more
resilient and that question is still
central to all the work that we do and
we are particularly interested in how we
can nudge people along this continuum to
nourish and nurture the qualities that
promote human flourishing in the early
part of my career I focused almost
exclusively on the negative side of the
equation on adversity on the brain
circuits that were important for
understanding why some people are more
vulnerable to stress why others may be
more likely to develop a depression or
anxiety and then something very
significant happened in my life in 1992
I first met his Holiness the Dalai Lama
and this picture of his holiness was
taken in Madison Wisconsin and he's
visited us several times and he was the
chief inspiration in our turning toward
the positive and in that critical moment
in 1992 he challenged me and he said why
can't you use the same tools of modern
neuroscience to study kindness and to
study compassion in addition to studying
anxiety and fear and depression and
stress and I didn't have a very good
answer for him on that day
other than that it's hard but you know
when we first began to study kindness we
first began to study anxiety and
depression that was hard too and we've
made some progress in that area so the
work that we and others have been doing
is predicated on a critical insight in
modern science the insight concerning
neuroplasticity our brain
are constantly changing constantly being
shaped by the forces around us but we
have typically very little awareness of
what those forces are our brains are
changing wittingly or unwittingly most
of the time it's unwittingly most of the
time were not aware and we also have
little control over those forces and the
invitation in the work that I'm sharing
with you today is that we can actually
take more responsibility for our own
brains by transforming our minds but
first let me share with you what some of
the consequences of having our brains
being shaped unwittingly are and I'd
like to focus on four challenges that
have been critical in our society today
and these challenges are failures of
well-being in very important ways the
first is distractibility research
indicates that if we take people out and
about in the world and we text them and
this has been done in a study that was
published a number of years ago very
influential study with several thousand
people we text them when we asked them
three questions the first question is
what are you doing right now
and they check off from a list of
activities second question where is your
mind right now is it focused on what
you're doing or is it focused elsewhere
and the third question is at this very
moment how happy or unhappy are you
here's what was found the average
American adult spends forty seven
percent of her or his waking life not
paying attention to what we're doing
folks
we could do better
and when they were not paying attention
to what they're doing they were
significantly less happy the scientific
paper upon which this is based
was titled a wandering mind is an
unhappy mind in addition there is a huge
increase in the incidence of attention
deficit disorders in children in this
country this is a graph showing a trend
over the last decade there are many
reasons for this increase but some of
them have to do with a genuine increase
in distractibility if we're all honest
with ourselves our nation is suffering
not simply from a fiscal deficit but
from an attention deficit we also are
suffering from loneliness despite the
fact that we're all so much more
interconnected 76% of middle-aged
Americans report that they have moderate
to high levels of loneliness and this
loneliness is not an ephemeral
subjective state it also impacts our
bodies our physical health recent
research shows that loneliness is
actually a more significant predictor by
more than a two-fold magnitude of early
mortality compared to obesity
so this exacts real tolls on our brains
and our bodies and again research shows
we can do better
negative self-talk in depression we all
have a narrative in our mind that we
carry around about who we are and
sometimes we have negative beliefs about
ourselves which can culminate in
depression and this turns out to be a
very serious problem depression is on
the rise if you look at trends just over
the last few years what you see is
is a very large increase particularly
among women over the last three years
alone there's been a 33 percent increase
in diagnosis of major depression in
women and this trend is occurring in
teens as well
these are disturbing trends in kids ages
12 through 17 and the gender difference
also is very unfortunately robust where
the incidence is much greater and
females and this trend is getting worse
over time and again the evidence
suggests that we can actually train our
mind and harness the power of
neuroplasticity to change these these
qualities in our mind suicide rates are
very disturbing during the Great
Depression there was a huge elevation
and those rates have come back down and
then since the year 2000 there has been
unfortunately a steep rise in suicide
rates and again this is not something
restricted to adults
our teams are showing more than doubling
over the last ten years in suicide so
that today in the United States
unfortunately more than one teenager
every single day is taking her or his
own life
there also is a pervasive loss of
meaning and purpose that people are
reporting and this loss is not simply
again a subjective quality but also
exacts a toll on our health and other
aspects of our well-being research shows
that a lack of purpose predicts an early
death in a recent study people who are
in their 60s with a low sense of purpose
had more than twice likelihood of dying
within five years compared to people who
reported a high sense of purpose so
again there are intimate connections
between our psychological well-being and
our systemic health each of these
challenges affect
the mind and the brain were not thriving
but the invitation is that we really
could be so we've developed a framework
for understanding a healthy mind and
this framework includes four pillars the
first pillar is awareness and awareness
includes the capacity to focus our
attention to resist distraction it also
includes a quality that psychologists
and neuroscientists call meta awareness
meta awareness is knowing what our minds
are doing how many of you have ever had
the experience of reading a book where
you're reading each word on a page and
you read one page you may read a second
page and after a few minutes you have
absolutely no idea what you've just read
that is an example of a lapse in met
awareness but the moment we recognize
that we've been lost and come back that
is a moment of meta awareness and we
have reason to believe that met
awareness is crucial actually it's
necessary we believe for real
transformation to occur the second
pillar of a healthy mind is connection
connection refers to those qualities
which nurture harmonious interpersonal
relationships
qualities like appreciation like
kindness like compassion having a
positive outlook and again the research
shows that it doesn't take much to start
activating these latent qualities which
can flourish and become stronger the
third pillar of a healthy mind is
insight and insight is about insight
into the narrative that we all have
about ourselves at the very extreme end
of
continuum there are people who have a
very negative narrative they have
negative self-beliefs and they hold
those beliefs to be a true description
of who they are that is a prescription
for depression and a healthy mind
entails changing our relationship to
this narrative not so much changing the
narrative itself but changing our
relationship to it so that we can look
at the narrative and see it for what it
is
what is this narrative it's a
constellation of thoughts and when we
can see it is that we can foster more
room more breathing room and lead to and
this leads to increased well-being
finally the last pillar of a healthy
mind is purpose and here we're talking
about having a sense that our life is
headed in a particular direction and
most importantly it is about taking more
and more of the activities in our lives
as belonging to this sense of purpose
can you envision living your life so
that taking out the garbage and doing
the laundry is still related to your
sense of purpose being able to broaden
it in this way is a very crucial
ingredient of a healthy mind
have you ever trained your mind research
from neuroscience leads us to understand
that there are two fundamentally
different kinds of learning one form of
learning we call declarative learning
which is learning about things I can
learn the value of kindness by sitting
down and studying texts about kindness
but this won't necessarily lead us to
become kinder we can teach people the
value of honesty but this will not
necessarily make them an honest person
in order to cultivate these qualities we
need a second form of learning and that
is called
procedural learning
neuroscience teaches us that these kinds
of learning operate through totally
different brain circuits we need both to
produce real transformation the wiring
in our brains is not fixed it's
adaptable and we can harness the power
of neuroplasticity to change our brain
let me give you one example this is an
example from research that we did where
we randomized people to a group that
received compassion training for two
weeks another group that received
training from cognitive therapy we put
people in the MRI scanner before and
after the two weeks of training and lo
and behold we see systematic differences
after just seven hours of practice our
brains can change in a remarkably rapid
period of time the changes that are
displayed here it changes in a circuit
that involved the prefrontal cortex and
the ventral striatum a circuit very
important for certain kinds of positive
emotions which gets strengthened after
just this short amount of practice so
these and other kinds of data indicate
that the brain really can change quite
quickly it doesn't mean that these
changes will last but it means that they
can be that they can occur they can
begin and with systematic practice they
will endure we view this as an urgent
public health need so we need to start
someplace I would recommend three
minutes a day when human beings first
evolved on this planet none of us were
brushing our teeth and yet today we all
do this is not part of our genome this
is a learned behavior
and it doesn't take much to start these
mechanisms in the brain to change so we
can do this when we're doing other
things we can do this while we're
commuting we can do this as we're
literally brushing our teeth we can do
this
as we're having our first cup of coffee
or
tea in the morning we can do this as
we're walking this can be incorporated
in routines of our daily life so we can
nourish our mind and through it we can
change the world we can reduce implicit
bias bias that gets under the skin this
is something that we've shown can occur
with strengthening connection we can
increase school achievement and we've
and others have shown this with training
and awareness we can reduce healthcare
costs potentially by cultivating
well-being as the connections that I've
Illustrated show we can cultivate a
strong sense of purpose we can reduce
distraction and we can increase
productivity and focus and I'd like to
end with just a one-minute short period
of practice to give you an experience
I'll taste of this so if you all just
sit for a moment put down your pens and
devices and I invite you to bring a
loved one into your mind in your heart
you can leave your eyes open or closed
and for those who are viewing this
online please share this one-minute with
us and as you bring this loved one into
your mind in your heart cultivate the
strong aspiration that they be happy and
be free of suffering and they share the
same wish for happiness and the same
wish to be free of suffering as all
human beings and you can envision a time
in their life when they maybe may have
been having some difficulty and you can
say a simple phrase in your mind may you
be happy may you be free of suffering
and simply notice whatever may come up
for you and then we can do this from
many categories of people including a
difficult person so I invite you to join
us on this journey and the very future
of humanity
we think depends on it thank you very
much
[Applause]